=-SF字幕同好會-=
本字幕僅供學習交流，嚴禁用於商業途徑
翻譯&校對：envelope@HDC noyhi@HDC
轉載請保留信息，歡迎有志之士加入，請在HDC致信hkwwcl
引自叛國罪條款：
From the Treaty of the Treason:
為使叛亂者贖罪，每個地區每年都要
In penance for their uprising,each district shall offer up
公開「抽籤」選擇一對年齡
在12-18歲的少年男女作為貢品
a male and female between the ages of 12 and 18 at a public 'reaping'.
這些貢品會被送至都城凱匹特監管
(註：凱匹特為施惠國的都城，對旗下12個行政區
具有絕對統治權，是「飢餓遊戲」的始作俑者)
These Tributes shall be delivered to the custody of the Capitol.
然後送至競技場，他們將在那裏戰鬥至死
直到剩下最後一名勝利者
（註：競技場，飢餓遊戲每屆都會選擇全新的比賽
場地，由荒廢土地改建而成；比賽後成為旅遊勝地）
And then transferred to a public arena where they will Fight to the Death, until a lone victor remains.
這個盛會自此永遠地被稱為
飢餓遊戲
Henceforth and forevermore this pageant shall be known as The Hunger Games.
我想這是我們的傳統
I think it's our tradition.
它源於我們國家歷史上極其慘痛的那段經歷
It comes out of a particularly painful
part of our history.
是的
Yes, yes.
但它已經成為使我們能夠治癒痛苦的方式
But it's been the way
we've been able to heal.
起初，這是對叛亂行為的警示
At first, it was a reminder of the rebellion.
- 叛亂地區必須因此而付出代價
- 對
- It was a price the districts had to pay.
- Yes.
但我認為現在更成熟了一些
But I think it has grown from that.
這可以讓我們團結在一起
I think it's something
that knits us all together.
作為連續三年的遊戲製作者
This is your third year as Gamemaker.
您的座右銘是什麼？
What defines your personal signature?
不！不！
No! No!
[12區]
[DISTRICT 12]
沒事，別怕，你只是在做夢，一個夢罷了
It's okay. It's okay. You were just dreaming.
You were dreaming.
我夢見被選中了
It was me.
我知道，但是事實不是這樣的
I know. I know. But it's not.
這是你的第一年，普利姆
你的名字只在那出現過一次
It's your first year, Prim.
Your name's only been in there once.
他們不會選你的
They're not gonna pick you.
再去睡會吧
Try to go to sleep.
我睡不著
I can't.
試試吧，躺下就睡著了
Just try. Just try.
在草叢深處
Deep in the meadow
在柳樹下
Under the willow
- 草墊床
- A bed of grass
- 軟軟的綠枕頭
- A soft green pillow
你還記得這歌？很好
You remember that song? Okay.
把它唱完，我得出去下
You finish it. I've got to go.
去哪？
Where?
我必須得走了
I've just got to go.
不過我會回來的，我愛你
But I'll be back. I love you
我還是要把你燉了
I'll still cook you.
[區域分界]
[禁止通行]
[DISTRICT BOUNDARY]
[NO ACCESS BEYOND THIS POINT]
[高壓電]
[HIGH VOLTAGE]
你打算怎麼獵殺它？
What are you gonna do with that
when you kill it?
該死，蓋爾！這並不好笑！
Damn you, Gale! It's not funny!
對於重達100磅的鹿你還能怎麼辦？凱特尼普
（注:女主角叫Katniss，為印地安語的慈菇之意，是伴水而生的植物，
根部可食用。由於發音類似，蓋爾昵稱她為Catnip，意為貓薄荷）
What are you gonna do
with a 100-pound deer, Catnip?
今天是抽籤日，到處都是維和部隊
It's Reaping Day.
The place is crawling with Peacekeepers.
我本打算把它賣給維和部隊的
I was gonna sell it to some Peacekeepers.
當然
Of course you were.
就像你不賣給他們似的
Like you don't sell to Peacekeepers.
不，不是今天
No. Not today.
這可是今年我看到的第一頭鹿
現在什麼都沒了
It was the first deer I've seen in a year.
Now I have nothing.
好吧
Okay.
如果他們不看了呢？只有一年
假使大家都不看飢餓遊戲了呢？
What if they did? Just one year.
What if everyone just stopped watching?
- 不會的，蓋爾
- 如果他們不看了呢？如果我們不看了呢？
- They won't, Gale.
- What if they did? What if we did?
不會的
Won't happen.
你會為自己喜歡的選手加油
一旦被殺你就會哭個不停
You root for your favorites.
You cry when they get killed.
- 真噁心
- 蓋爾
- It's sick.
- Gale.
如果沒人看，他們就沒這個遊戲
If no one watches,
then they don't have a game.
再簡單不過
It's as simple as that.
- 什麼？
- 沒什麼
- What?
- Nothing.
- 好吧，你就笑我吧
- 我沒笑你
- Fine. Laugh at me.
- I'm not laughing at you.
我們能做到，你知道嗎？
We could do it, you know?
離開這，在樹林裏生活，這就是我們要做的
Take off, live in the woods.
It's what we do anyway.
他們會把我們抓回來的
They'd catch us.
也許不會
Well, maybe not.
割掉我們的舌頭，甚至更糟
我們跑不出五英里
Cut out our tongues, or worse.
We wouldn't make it five miles.
不，我已經跑出五英里了，我走的那條路
No, I'd get five miles. I'd go that way.
我這還有普利姆，你也有弟弟
I have Prim, and you have your brothers.
他們可以一起來
They can come, too.
讓普利姆到樹林裏生活？
Prim in the woods?
也許未必
Or maybe not.
我沒要過孩子
I'm never having kids.
我也許會要，如果不在這兒生活的話
I might, if I didn't live here.
- 但你就在這生活
- 我知道，我是說假如
- But you do live here.
- I know, but if I didn't.
差點忘了
I forgot.
給
Here.
天吶！真的嗎？
Oh, my God! Is this real?
當然是真的，我用一個松鼠換的
Yeah. Better be. Cost me a squirrel.
飢餓遊戲快樂
Happy Hunger Games.
「希望好運永遠站在你這邊」
"And may the odds be ever in your favor."
今天你名字被用多少次了？
How many times is your name in today?
42次
Forty-two.
我看好運並不站在我這邊
Guess the odds aren't exactly in my favor.
謝謝，閨女
Thank you, girl.
這是什麼？
What's this?
這是「自由夢幻」
That's a Mockingjay.
多少錢？
How much?
- 拿著吧，歸你了
- 謝謝
- You keep it. It's yours.
- Thank you.
媽媽
Mom.
看看你！
Look at you!
真漂亮
You look beautiful.
但最好把這個掖在後面，小鴨子
But you better tuck in that tail,little duck.
我也給你準備了點東西
I laid something out for you, too.
好的
Okay.
現在你也很漂亮了
Now you look beautiful, too.
真希望我能像你一樣
Wish I looked like you.
不，我希望像你一樣漂亮，小鴨子
No. l wish I looked like you, little duck.
嘿，想看看今天我給你帶什麼了嗎？
Hey. You want to see what I got you today?
這是自由夢幻胸針，可以保護你
It's a Mockingjay pin. To protect you.
只要你戴著它，就不會有霉運
And as long as you have it,
nothing bad will happen to you.
好麼？我保證
Okay? I promise.
普利姆，沒事的
Prim, it's okay. It's okay.
現在開始登記了，好嗎？
Okay. It's time to sign in now. Okay?
他們會戳一下你的手指取一點點血
They're gonna prick your finger
just to take a little bit of blood.
- 你之前不是說…
- 我知道
- You didn't say...
- I know.
並不會很痛，一點點而已
It doesn't hurt much. Just a little.
好麼？登記完去和那些小朋友坐一起
然後我會去找你，明白麼？
Okay? Go sit down there with the little kids.
I'll find you after. Okay?
下一個
Next.
繼續，下一個
Go ahead. Next.
下一個
Next.
沒事的
It's okay.
歡迎！歡迎，歡迎
Welcome! Welcome, welcome.
飢餓遊戲快樂
Happy Hunger Games.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
現在，開始之前，我們有一部特別的影片
Now, before we begin,
we have a very special film.
為了大家從凱匹特一路帶回來的
Brought to you all the way from The Capitol.
戰爭，可怕的戰爭
War. Terrible war.
戰爭
War.
可怕的戰爭，寡婦、孤兒和失去母親的孩子
Terrible war.
Widows, orphans, a motherless child.
暴動使我們的國家陷入內亂
This was the uprising that rocked our land.
13區背叛了一直哺育、熱愛
Thirteen districts rebelled against
the country that fed them,
和保護他們的祖國
loved them, protected them.
同胞之前互相殘殺直至所剩無幾
Brother turned on brother
until nothing remained.
之後便迎來和平，這是一次艱難的戰鬥，慘痛的勝利
And then came the peace,
hard fought, sorely won.
人們浩劫餘生，一個新紀元誕生了
A people rose up from the ashes,
and a new era was born.
但自由是需要付出代價的，叛徒被擊敗了
But freedom has a cost.
And the traitors were defeated.
做為國民我們發誓永遠不會讓悲劇重演
We swore as a nation
we would never know this treason again.
所以法律規定施惠國的不同區域每年
And so it was decreed that each year
the various districts of Panem
要奉上一對少年男女作為貢品
would offer up, in tribute,
one young man and woman
為了榮譽、勇氣和奉獻戰鬥至死
to fight to the death in a pageant of honor,
courage, and sacrifice.
唯一的倖存者會變得非常富有
The lone victor, bathed in riches,
would serve as a reminder
以此彰顯我們的慷慨和寬恕
of our generosity and our forgiveness.
這就是我們銘記過往
This is how we remember our past.
保護未來的方式
This is how we safeguard our future.
我很喜歡這段話！
I just love that!
現在，是時候讓我們選擇
Now, the time has come for us to select
一對勇敢的年輕男女
one courageous young man and woman
作為第74屆年度飢餓遊戲12區榮譽代表了
for the honor of representing District 12
in the 74th Annual Hunger Games.
像往常一樣，女士優先
As usual, ladies first.
普利姆羅斯·埃弗丁
Primrose Everdeen.
親愛的，你在哪？
Where are you, dear?
上來吧
Come on up.
來吧
Well, come on up.
普利姆！普利姆！
Prim! Prim!
不，不！
No. No!
我當志願者！我要當志願者！
I volunteer! I volunteer!
我自願作為貢品！
I volunteer as Tribute!
我們擁有一位志願者，市長先生
I believe we have a volunteer, Mr. Mayor.
普利姆，你得馬上離開這，快走
Prim, you need to get out of here.
You need to get out of here.
- 不！不！
- 去找媽媽！
- No!No!
- Go find Mom!
- 普利姆，現在去找媽媽，很抱歉
- 不！
- Prim, go find Mom right now. I'm so sorry.
- No!
- 去找媽媽，普利姆，快走！去找媽媽！
- 不！不！不！
- Go find Mom. Prim, leave! Go find Mom.
- No!No!No!
不！不！不！
- Come on.
12區出現了戲劇性的轉變
A dramatic turn of events here in District 12.
好了
Yes, well.
12區史上第一位志願者
帶她上來
District 12's very first volunteer.
Bring her up.
來，親愛的
Come on, dear.
你叫什麼名字？
What's your name?
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Katniss Everdeen.
我打賭她一定是你妹妹，對嗎？
Well, I bet my hat that was your sister,
wasn't it?
是的
Yes.
讓我們對第一位志願者，凱特尼斯·埃弗丁，報以熱烈掌聲!
Let's have a big hand for
our very first volunteer, Katniss Everdeen.
現在輪到男孩了
And now for the boys.
皮塔·麥拉克
Peeta Mellark.
人齊了
Here we are.
這就是我們12區的貢品
Our Tributes from District 12.
好了，你們倆握個手吧
Well, go on, you two, shake hands.
飢餓遊戲快樂
Happy Hunger Games.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
給你三分鐘
You have three minutes.
沒事的
It's okay.
普利姆，普利姆，沒事
普利姆，我沒多少時間了
Prim. Prim. It's okay.
Prim, I don't have much time.
普利姆，聽著，你會沒事的
不要從他們那拿走額外的食物
Prim. Listen. You're gonna be okay.
Don't take any extra food from them.
這不值得多次記錄你的名字，好嗎？
It isn't worth putting your name in
more times. Okay?
聽著，普利姆，蓋爾會帶你玩的
你可以把羊奶酪賣掉
Listen, Prim. Gale will bring you game.
You can sell cheese from your goat.
要努力贏得比賽，也許你可以的
Just try to win. Maybe you can.
當然
Of course.
或許我能贏的，我很聰明，知道麼？
And maybe I can. I am smart, you know?
- 你會打獵
- 對呀
- And you can hunt.
- Exactly.
保護你
To protect you.
謝謝
Thank you.
（註：所有12-18歲的少男少女均可申請
食物兌換卷，領取1人1年份的糧食與油）
（這份優惠同樣需要付出相應的代價
一張兌換券等於增加一次抽籤名條）
（對於窮人來說無異於提高自己成為貢品的幾率
因此凱特尼斯在離開前囑咐妹妹不要領取食物兌換券）
你不能再被選為貢品了
You can't tune out again.
- 不會的
- 不，你不能。別像爸爸死的時候一樣
- I won't.
- No, you can't. Not like when Dad died.
我不能再到那了，你就是她的一切
I won't be there anymore. You're all she has.
無論你是怎麼想的，你必須為了她去那，明白嗎？
No matter what you feel, you have to
be there for her. Do you understand?
別哭
Don't cry.
別哭，別哭，別
Don't cry. Don't. Don't.
- 時間到了
- 普利姆，沒事的
- It's time.
- Prim, it's okay.
- 普利姆，別擔心，沒事，普利姆
- 不！不！不！
- Prim, it's okay. It's okay, Prim.
- No!No!No!
我保證，普利姆
I promise, Prim.
- 我很好
- 我知道
- I'm fine.
- Yeah, I know.
真沒事
I am.
聽我說，你比他們任何一個人都優秀
Listen to me. You're stronger than they are.
You are.
- 弄一個弓
- 他們可能沒有…
- Get to a bow.
- They may not have...
如果你足夠優秀他們會想辦法的
They will if you show them
how good you are.
人們只是想要一場好看的比賽
僅此而已
They just want a good show.
That's all they want.
如果他們沒有弓，你就做一個，好麼？
If they don't have a bow,
then you make one, okay?
你知道如何狩獵
You know how to hunt.
動物
Animals.
這沒什麼不同，凱特尼斯
It's no different, Katniss.
我們有24個人，蓋爾，只有一個人能活著
There's 24 of us, Gale. Only one comes out.
這個人一定是你
Yeah. And it's gonna be you.
好了
Okay.
照顧好她們，蓋爾
無論怎樣，別讓他們挨餓
Take care of them, Gale.
Whatever you do, don't let them starve.
- 走吧
- 我會盡快再見到你的，好嗎？
- Let's go.
- I'll see you soon, okay?
你們倆會喜歡的
You two are in for a treat.
水晶吊燈，白金門把手，速度快極了
Crystal chandeliers, platinum doorknobs,
and it flies.
我們會在凱匹特停留不到兩天
We'll be at The Capitol
in less than two days.
現在，在你做其他事之前…
Now, before you do anything else...
200英里每小時，幾乎沒什麼感覺
200 miles per hour,
and you can barely feel a thing.
即使你們在這，哪怕只有一小會
I think it's one of the wonderful things about
this opportunity,
我想這次機遇也是一件很美妙的事情
that even though you're here
and even though it's just for a little while,
你們可以享受這裏的一切
you get to enjoy all of this.
我去找黑密斯，他可能在酒吧車廂那
I'm going to find Haymitch.
He's probably in the bar car.
你之前見過他嗎？
Have you ever met him?
黑密斯？
Haymitch?
你知道的，凱特尼斯，他是我們的導師，贏過一次比賽
You know, Katniss, he is our mentor.
He did win this thing once.
好吧，如果你不想和我交談，我理解
Look, you know,
if you don't want to talk, I understand,
但我不認為想得到一點幫助有什麼錯的
but I just don't think there's anything wrong
with getting a little bit of help.
恭喜
Congratulations.
冰塊呢？
Where's the ice?
不知道
I don't know.
可以坐下嗎？
May I?
好的，我們什麼時候開始？
Okay, so... So when do we start?
太心切了
So eager.
多數人都沒這麼猴急
Most of you aren't in such a hurry.
我想知道計劃是什麼，你是我倆的導師啊
Yeah. I wanna know what the plan is.
You're our mentor.
- 你應該…
- 導師？
- You're supposed to go...
- Mentor?
是啊，我們的導師
Yeah, our mentor.
你應該告訴我們如何獲得贊助並給些建議
You're supposed to tell us
how to get sponsors and give us advice.
好吧
Okay.
做好有可能將死的準備
Embrace the probability
of your imminent death.
要知道，在你們心中，我救不了你們
And know, in your heart,
that there's nothing I can do to save you.
那你為什麼還在這？
So why are you here then?
不愁吃喝
The refreshments.
好吧，夠了
Okay, I think that's enough of that.
你把我的酒碰灑了，這可是條新褲子
You made me spill my drink.
These are brand new pants.
你懂的，等我回屋會把它喝完的
You know, I think I'll go
finish this in my room.
他快醒酒了
He's gonna come around.
沒用的
It's no use.
我去和他談談
I'm gonna go talk to him.
我們有兩位非常合適的16歲隊員
We have two very fit 16-year-olds.
當然，他們總是能夠提供優秀的競爭對手
Of course, of course.
They always provide pretty good opponents.
是啊
Yes, yes, they do.
- 還記得這一年嗎？
- 當然
- Do you remember this year?
- Of course.
我最喜歡的比賽之一，阿瑞納斯表現很棒
One of my favorite years.
And one of my favorite Arenas.
利用荒廢城市裏的碎石
The use of the rubble in the ruined city...
真令人興奮
Very exciting.
這個時刻
And this moment here,
你永遠不會忘記
this moment is a moment
that you never forget.
是的
Yes.
當貢品變成勝利者的時刻
The moment when a Tribute
becomes a victor.
- 首先，你會被凍死
- 不會的，我可以點火
- You'd freeze to death first.
- No, because I'd light a fire.
是個找死的好辦法
That's a good way to get killed.
什麼找死的好辦法？
What's a good way to get killed?
有意思，怎麼不過來和我們一起聊聊？
Joy. Why don't you join us?
我只是給些生存建議
I was just giving some life-saving advice.
比如說？
Like what?
我剛才問他如何找到避難所
I was just asking about how to find shelter.
這些遲早有用，實際上你們還活著
Which would come in handy if,
in fact, you were still alive.
你怎麼找到避難所的？
How do you find shelter?
果醬給我
Pass the jam.
你怎麼找到避難所的？
How do you find shelter?
寶貝，讓我喘口氣吧
Give me a chance to wake up , sweetheart.
作為導師，這活可不輕鬆
This mentoring is very taxing stuff.
能把果醬遞給我嗎？
Can you pass the marmalade?
那可是紅木！
That is mahogany!
看看你，對餐具墊發什麼火
Look at you. Just killed a placemat.
你真想知道如何才能生存下來嗎？
You really want to know how to stay alive?
你得讓觀眾喜歡你
You get people to like you.
並不是你所期望的那樣
Not what you were expecting?
當你處於遊戲當中，你會挨餓挨凍
Well, when you're in the middle of
The Games and you're starving or freezing,
水、刀子，甚至是火柴
some water, a knife, or even some matches
都關乎你的生死
can mean the difference
between life and death.
這些東西取決於贊助商
And those things only come from sponsors.
想獲得贊助商的青睞，你必須讓觀眾喜歡你
And to get sponsors,
you have to make people like you.
寶貝，現在你離一個好的開頭並不遠了
And right now, sweetheart,
you're not off to a real good start.
就是那
There it is.
真壯觀！
It's huge!
不可思議
That's incredible.
皮塔，我愛你
Peeta, I love you.
來，來啊
Come on. Come on.
你最好留著這把刀，他清楚自己在做什麼
You better keep this knife.
He knows what he's doing.
現在你已經看到他們了
So now that you've seen them,
你認為今年的新選手怎麼樣？
what do you think about
this year's crop of recruits?
有什麼值得期待的亮點嗎？
Are there any surprises
that we can expect this year?
僅從抽籤來看真的很難說
It's really hard to tell just from a Reaping,
- 但我認為這將是一場非常有趣的混戰
- 沒錯
-but I think this is a very interesting mix.
- Yes.
而且這次還有一位邊遠區域的志願者
And whenever you have a volunteer
from an outlying district,
這絕對是個看點
that's something you can't ignore.
那是什麼？
What's that?
我們只是在談論在你見西納之前
We're just saying we might need
to hose you down again
可能需要再幫你沖洗一遍
before we take you to Cinna.
替妹妹作為貢品，這是我見過的最勇敢的行為
That was one of the bravest things
I've ever seen. With your sister?
- 我叫西納
- 凱特尼斯
- My name's Cinna.
- Katniss.
對於你的遭遇感到很抱歉
I'm sorry that this happened to you,
我會盡我所能幫助你
and I'm here to help you
in any way that I can.
多數人只是恭喜我罷了
Most people just congratulate me.
我不會那麼想
Well, I don't see the point in that.
今晚有貢品巡遊活動
So tonight, they have the Tribute Parade.
我要讓全世界看到你有多漂亮
I'm gonna take you out
and show you off to the world.
你在這就是為了打扮我？
So you're here to make me look pretty?
我是為了讓觀眾對有個好印象
I'm here to help you make an impression.
通常他們根據貢品所在區域特點來打扮
Now, usually they dress people
in the clothes from their district.
- 好啊，我們那全是礦工
- 我不會那麼幹的
- Yeah, we're always coalminers.
- Yeah, but I don't wanna do that.
我要做的一定會令他們難忘
I wanna do something
that they're gonna remember.
他們跟你說過如何才能獲得贊助商嗎？
Did they explain
about trying to get sponsors?
說了，但我並不擅長交朋友
Yeah, but I'm not very good
at making friends.
走著瞧吧
We'll see.
我想有膽量的人
I just think somebody that brave
不應該穿得太隨便，對嗎？
shouldn't be dressed up
in some stupid costume, now should they?
希望如此
I hope not.
我保證這很安全
Okay, this is safe. I promise.
這不是真正的火焰，衣服是量身定做的
不會感到任何不適
It's not real fire. These suits are built
so you won't feel a thing.
看起來真的很合身
Looks pretty real to me.
就是這意思
Well, that's the idea.
準備好了嗎？
You ready?
- 別害怕
- 我不怕
- Don't be afraid.
- I'm not afraid.
超過10萬人正迫不及待的等著觀賞今年的貢品
Over 100,000 people craning
to get a glimpse of this year's Tributes.
贊助商們也是第一次看到這些貢品
And the sponsors get to see the Tributes
for the first time.
此刻的重要性無需贅言
The importance of this moment
cannot be overstated.
很好
Very nice.
第一輛戰車入場倒計時開始，15,14，13…
First chariot on my count, in 15, 14, 13...
來了，他們來啦，今年的貢品們
There they are. There they are.
This year's Tributes.
真令人激動
It's the most exciting part.
雞皮疙瘩都起來了
It just gives you goose bumps.
太喜歡這些設計師了
And don't you love how the stylists,
他們是怎麼把每個區域選手的特色
如此清晰呈現出來的？
they so clearly are able to
reflect the character of each district?
- 沒錯，第4區的選手來了
- 是啊
- Right. Right. There's District 4.
- Yes.
- 魚類裝扮
- 我看見了
- Fishing.
- I get it.
- 我喜歡
- 很不錯
- I like it.
- That's very good.
在他們後面有兩位電廠工人，對嗎？
And behind them,
we have two power plant workers. Right?
然後呢…
And then...
最後那個是什麼？
What is that in the background?
來吧，他們喜歡這樣。
Come on. They'll love it.
耶！
Yeah!
看到了嗎？我喜歡
Now see that? I love that.
兩個年輕人高舉緊握在一起的雙手
Two young people
holding their hands up, saying,
喊著「我為來自12區感到自豪，我們不會被忽視的」
"I'm proud I come from District 12.
We will not be overlooked."
- 當然不會
- 真棒我喜歡
- Nope.
- I love that!
所有人的注意力都集中在他們身上
People are sure gonna be paying attention
to them right now.
準備好了
And we're ready.
斯諾總統，該你了
President Snow, you're live.
歡迎
Welcome.
貢品們，歡迎你們的到來！
Tributes, we welcome you.
對於你們的勇氣和奉獻精神我們深表敬意
We salute your courage and your sacrifice.
祝願你們
And we wish you
飢餓遊戲快樂
Happy Hunger Games.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
簡直難以置信
That was amazing.
所有人都在討論你們
We are all
anybody's going to be talking about.
真夠大膽的
So brave.
你確信自己呆在我這團烈火旁會沒事嗎？
Are you sure you should be
near an open flame?
火焰道具嗎？你確信…
Fake flame? Are you sure you...
咱們上樓吧
Let's go upstairs.
每個區域都有屬於自己的樓層
So, each of the districts get their own floor.
因為你們來自12區，所以閣樓是你們的
And because you're from 12,
you get the penthouse.
來
Come on.
這是客廳
So this is the living room.
我知道
I know, I know.
你們的臥室在這
Now, your rooms are right over here.
在晚餐開始之前為什麼不先去洗個澡呢？
Why don't you go clean yourselves up
a little before dinner?
兩周內，會有23個人死掉
In two weeks, 23 of you will be dead.
只有一個倖存者
One of you will be alive.
這取決於你們是否在意接下來的四天
Who that is depends on how well
you pay attention over the next four days,
尤其是我將要說的這些事
particularly to what I'm about to say.
首先，不要和其它選手打鬥
First, no fighting with the other Tributes.
在競技場你們有的是時間
You'll have plenty of time for that
in the Arena.
有四個必修練習，其餘的是個人訓練
There are four compulsory exercises.
The rest will be individual training.
我建議你們不要忽視生存技能
My advice is don't ignore the survival skills.
每個人都想奪取利劍
Everybody wants to grab a sword,
但多數人都會死於自然因素
but most of you will die
from natural causes.
10%的人死於感染，20%的人死於脫水
10% from infection, 20% from dehydration.
暴曬能像刀子一樣輕易致人死地
Exposure can kill as easily as a knife.
- 傑森，我的刀呢？
- 我沒碰你的刀
- Jason, where's my knife, huh?
- I didn't touch your knife.
- 我就把刀放那了！
- 別碰我，我沒拿你的刀！
- I put my knife right there!
- Don't touch me. I didn't touch your knife!
- 你拿了！
- 我沒拿！
- Yes, you took my knife!
- I didn't touch your knife!
- 你拿我的刀了，騙子！
- 我沒拿
- You took my knife, you liar!
- I didn't touch your knife.
- 騙子！
- 我沒拿！
- You liar!
- I didn't touch your knife!
臭小子！他拿我刀！
You little punk! He took my knife!
- 放開我！
- 我一直坐在這
- Get off me!
- I'm just sitting here.
我現在就把我幹掉，臭小子！
I'll finish you right now, kid!
好啊，我在競技場等你
Actually, better yet, I'll wait for the Arena.
我第一個就去收拾你，給我小心點
You're the first one I get,
so watch your back.
- 大家退後！
- 你知道你得罪誰了，臭小子！
- Everybody, back in line!
- You know who you're messing with, kid!
他是職業幹這個的，知道什麼意思嗎？
He's a Career. You know what that is?
- 從第1區來的
- 還有第2區
- From District 1.
- And 2.
他們18歲前都在專門的培訓機構訓練
然後作為志願者參賽
They train in a special academy
until they're 18. Then they volunteer.
這也就意味著他們很難對付
By that point, they're pretty lethal.
但他們沒有任何特殊待遇
But they don't receive any special treatment.
實際上，他們和你們呆在相同的房間內
In fact, they stay in the exact
same apartment as you do.
他們沒有餐後甜點可以吃，而你們卻有
And I don't think they let them have dessert.
And you can.
他們實力有多強？
So how good are they?
顯然他們很優秀，差不多每年都會獲勝，但…
Obviously they're pretty good.
They win it almost every year, but...
差不多
Almost.
他們太自大了
...they can be arrogant.
自大是個嚴重問題
And arrogance can be a big problem.
聽說你會射箭
I hear you can shoot.
還好吧
I'm all right.
她射箭技術很好的，我爸買過她的松鼠
No, she's better than all right.
My father buys her squirrels.
他說她每次都是箭無虛發
He says she hits them
right in the eye every time.
- 皮塔很強壯
- 什麼？
- Peeta's strong.
- What?
他可以把100磅的麵粉舉過頭頂，我見過
He can throw a 100-pound sack
of flour right over his head. I've seen it.
好吧，我可不會用一袋麵粉殺人
Okay, well, I'm not gonna kill
anybody with a sack of flour.
但你可以用更好的方式獲勝
No, but you might have
a better chance of winning
如果有人拿刀過來
if somebody comes after you with a knife.
我贏不了！贏不了！懂嗎？
I have no chance of winning!
None! All right?
這是真的，大家都知道
It's true. Everybody knows it.
你知道我媽怎麼說的嗎？
You know what my mother said?
他說12區可能會有一個勝者
She said District 12
might finally have a winner.
但她說的不是我
But she wasn't talking about me.
是你
She was talking about you.
我不太餓
I'm not very hungry.
我也吃完了
I'm done, too.
把那個金屬東西扔過去
Throw that metal thing over there.
什麼？
What?
不，黑密斯說過不讓我們展露自己的才能
No. Haymitch said we're not supposed
to show our skills.
我不管黑密斯怎麼說的
I don't care what Haymitch said.
那幾個傢伙視你為砧板魚肉
Those guys are looking at you
like you're a meal.
扔過去
Throw it.
嗨
Hi.
Hey.
你怎麼做到的？
How did you do that?
我過去經常在麵包店做蛋糕美化工作
I used to decorate the cakes
down at the bakery.
給你看看
I'll show you.
看到了嗎？
See?
看到了
Yeah.
有人跟著你
Hey, I think you have a shadow.
明天他們會把你們一個接一個的帶進去
並且評估你們的能力
Tomorrow, they'll bring you in one by one
and evaluate you.
這點很重要，因為打分較高的意味著會有更多的贊助
This is important, because higher ratings
will mean sponsors.
是時候嶄露頭角了
This is the time to show them everything.
在那會有個弓，你一定要好好利用
There'll be a bow. Make sure you use it.
皮塔，你也一定要展示出你的力量
Peeta, you make sure to show your strength.
他們會從第1區開始，所以你們會排在最後
They'll start with District 1,
so the two of you will go last.
不知道該怎麼說，總之一定要讓他們記住你們
I don't know how else to put this.
Make sure they remember you.
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Katniss Everdeen.
嘿，凱特尼斯？
Hey, Katniss?
好好表現
Shoot straight.
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Katniss Everdeen.
12區的
District 12.
嘿，嘿，嘿
Hey, hey, hey-
嘿，誰點的乳豬？誰點的乳豬？嘿！
Hey, who ordered this pig?
Who ordered this pig? Hey!
你吃過乳豬沒？
Did you get some pig yet?
謝謝，僅供您參考
Thank you for your consideration.
- 你瘋了嗎？
- 我太生氣了
- Are you crazy?
- I just got mad.
生氣？
Mad?
你得意識到你的不良舉動會影響整個團隊
不只是你自己
You realize that your actions reflect badly
on all of us. Notjust you.
他們只是想要一場好看的比賽，沒事的
They just want a good show. It's fine.
這麼沒禮貌你覺得會怎麼樣，西納！
會怎麼樣？
How about it's just bad manners, Cinna!
How about that?
好吧，我希望你注意到我們的形勢很嚴峻
Well, finally! I hope you noticed
we have a serious situation.
幹得漂亮，寶貝
Nice shooting, sweetheart.
當你射中蘋果時他們什麼反應？
What did they do when you shot the apple?
他們都驚呆了
Well, they looked pretty startled.
耶
Yeah.
你說什麼來著？「謝謝…」
Now, what did you say? "Thanks for..."
- 謝謝，僅供您參考
- 「…供您參考」
- Thanks for your consideration.
-"...your consideration."
天才！天才！
Genius! Genius.
如果遊戲製作者想把我們踢出局的話
我想就沒這麼好笑了
I don't think we're gonna find this funny
if the Gamemakers decide to take it out...
踢誰？她？
On who? On her?
還是他？
On him?
我認為他們已經具備參賽資格了
放輕鬆，喝一杯
I think they already have.
Loosen your corset, have a drink.
我原本會不惜一切代價看到結果的
I would have given anything to see it.
正如你們所知道的，經過三天的仔細評估
As you know, the Tributes were rated
on a scale of 1 to 12
1至12區的貢品評分結果出來了
after three days of careful evaluation.
遊戲管理人得知了一個非常意外的…
The Gamekeepers would like
to acknowledge that it was an exceptional...
來自第1區的，漫威，9分
From District 1, Marvel, with a score of nine.
來自第2區的，卡托，10分
From District 2, Cato, with a score of 10.
克勞芙，10分
Clove, with a score of 10.
來自第3區的…
來自第4區的…
From District 3...
From District 4, with a score of...
來自第7區的
From District 7...
來自第8區的…
From District 8...
茹，7分
And Rue with a score of seven.
最後一個區了
Now our final district.
來自第12區的，皮塔·麥拉克
From District 12. Peeta Mellark.
8分
A score of eight.
- 棒極了
- 皮塔！
- Excellent.
- Peeta!
精彩
Bravo.
- 我們能做到的
- 幹得好
- We can work with that.
- Good job.
最後一位
And finally,
來自第12區的
from District 12,
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Katniss E verdeen.
分數是…
With a score of...
11分！
Eleven.
- 凱特尼斯！
- 難以置信！
- Katniss!
- Outstanding!
- 太好了！
- 11分？
- Yes!
- Eleven?
恭喜你
Congratulations.
我以為他們恨死我了
I thought they hated me.
他們喜歡你的勇氣
They must have liked your guts.
敬凱特尼斯·埃弗丁，燃燒女孩！
To Katniss Everdeen, The Girl on Fire!
天吶
Goodness. We are.
有個11分？
An 11?
她應得的
She earned it.
她把箭射在你腦袋上
She shot an arrow at your head.
是蘋果上
Well, at an apple.
離你腦袋也不遠了
Near your head.
坐下
Sit down.
塞內卡，你想想為什麼我們要選出一名勝者？
Seneca, why do you think we have a winner?
您的意思是？
What do you mean?
我的意思是為什麼要一個人活下來？
I mean, why do we have a winner?
如果我們只是威脅其它的區域
I mean, if we just wanted to
intimidate the districts,
為什麼不隨機選24個人組到一起讓他們立刻比賽呢？
why not round up 24 of them at random
and execute them all at once?
這樣多塊
Be a lot faster.
希望
Hope.
希望什麼？
Hope?
希望
Hope.
這是唯一強於恐懼的
It is the only thing stronger than fear.
一點希望可以讓人絕處逢生
希望太大的話是很危險的
A little hope is effective.
A lot of hope is dangerous.
火花可以有，但一定得能控制住
A spark is fine, as long as it's contained.
所以…
So...
讓一切都在可掌控的範圍內
So contain it.
好的
Right.
她目不轉睛的盯著我身上的珠寶
So she's staring at all my jewels.
She cannot take her eyes off of them.
- 是啊，從上到下打量一遍
- 說真的，這太無禮了
- Well, look at all that that you're wearing.
- Frankly, it was rude.
黑密斯，一起來吧
Haymitch, you should join us.
晚餐有你的最愛
We're having some of
your favorite for dinner.
那太好了
Lovely.
- 皮塔呢？
- 他在房間裏
- Where's Peeta?
- He's in his room.
聽著，明天是最後一天
Now, listen, tomorrow's the last day.
比賽前他們讓我們和自己的隊員呆在一起
And they let us work with our own Tributes
right before The Games,
所以咱倆9點前得呆在一起
so you and I will be going down at 9:00.
他呢？
What about him?
他說從現在開始想一個人訓練
He says he wants to be trained
on his own from now on.
什麼？
What?
這個時候還說這種事，贏家只有一個，別忘了
This kind of thing does happen at this point.
There's only one winner, right?
巧克力草莓還沒上來呢
We should have some
chocolate-covered strawberries.
- 噢，我喜歡吃
- 能不能行了
- Oh, my, yes.
- Please.
女士們，先生們，歡迎我們的節目主持人
Ladies and gentlemen,
your master of ceremonies,
凱撒·弗裏克曼
Caesar Flickerman!
謝謝大家！謝謝！
Thank you! Thank you!
歡迎，歡迎觀看第74屆年度飢餓遊戲大賽！
Welcome, welcome, welcome
to the 74th Annual Hunger Games!
大約5分鐘後，他們所有人都將到舞台上來
Now, in about five minutes,
they're all going to be out here.
所有你們瞭解的選手們齊聚一堂
All of the Tributes that you've heard about.
激動嗎？
Are you excited?
我聽不見！
Let me hear it!
太棒了
Amazing.
我並不覺得怎麼樣
I don't feel amazing.
難道你不覺得自己很漂亮嗎？
Don't you know how beautiful you look?
不覺得，我也不知道怎麼才能讓別人喜歡上我
No. And I don't know
how to make people like me.
- 你怎麼討別人喜歡的？
- 你已經讓我喜歡上你了
- How do you make people like you?
- Well, you made me like you.
這不一樣，我還不夠好
That's different. I wasn't trying.
就是這樣，做自己就行，我會一直在那
Exactly. Just be yourself,
I'll be there the whole time.
你只要假裝和我說話就行，好嗎？
And just pretend
that you're talking to me. Okay?
好吧
Okay.
讓我們瞧瞧她是否真的光芒閃耀
Let's see if she does indeed shine.
掌聲歡迎格裏姆！
Let's have a warm round of applause
for Glimmer!
格裏姆，準備好了嗎？
Glimmer, are you prepared?
當然，凱撒，早就準備好了
Yes, Caesar, I am very prepared.
我喜歡，你很自信
I like it. That's assurance.
That's self-assurance.
- 難道你不覺得嗎？
- 就像你看到的一樣…
- Don't you think?
- And, as you can see...
我穿的是我們自己設計的服裝
...I'm wearing one of our own creations.
請報以熱烈掌聲！
A big round of applause!
漫威！
Marvel!
歡迎，克勞芙
Welcome, Clove.
- 很榮幸代表我的區域參賽
- 你是個鬥士
- It's an honor representing my district.
- You're a fighter.
我準備好了，我可不友善，隨時出發
I'm prepared. I'm vicious. I'm ready to go.
卡托！
Cato!
我發現如果自己能夠接受現在的情況
I find that if I can apply myself
to the situation present,
我一定會有辦法獲勝的
I will be able to figure it out.
謝謝，很高興見到你
非常感謝
Thank you. Lovely to see you.
Thank you so much.
你會爬樹
Good. So you can climb trees.
動作很敏捷，你是獵人麼？
You're pretty quick. And are you a hunter?
還是收集果實的？
A gatherer?
從第12區來的，第12區…
From District 12, District 12...
被大家所熟知的燃燒女孩！
You know her as The Girl on Fire!
我們稱她為可愛的凱特尼斯·埃弗丁
Well, we know her
as the lovely Katniss Everdeen!
歡迎！歡迎！
Welcome! Welcome.
歡迎！
Welcome.
那天你的入場很特別
Well, that was quite an entrance
you made the other day.
你說什麼？
What?
我想某人有點緊張
I think someone's a little nervous.
我是說在不久前貢品巡遊那天
I said that was quite an entrance
that you made
你的入場方式很特別
at the Tribute Parade the other day.
想和我們談談這個嗎？
Do you want to tell us about it?
好，我只是希望別被燒死了
Well, I was just hoping that
I wouldn't burn to death.
當你從戰車上下來的時候
When you came out of that chariot,
不得不說，我的心臟都停止跳動了
I have to say, my heart stopped.
你們也有類似的感覺吧？
Did any of you experience this as well?
心跳停止了
My heart stopped.
我也一樣
So did mine.
和我說說那火焰吧，是真的嗎？
Now, tell me about the flames. Are they real?
是的
Yes.
事實上今天我也帶來了，你們想看嗎？
In fact, I'm wearing them today.
Would you like to see?
等一下，這安全嗎？
Wait, wait, wait. Is it safe?
當然
Yes.
觀眾們，你們是怎麼想的？
What do you think, folks?
我想一定會同意
I think that's a yes.
淡定，淡定
Steady. Steady.
太好看了，謝謝
Lovely. Thank you.
真了不起，凱特尼斯，太了不起了
That was really something.
Katniss, that was something.
了不起，謝謝你的表演
That was something. Thank you for that.
還有一個問題
I have one more question for you.
關於你的妹妹
It's about your sister.
當你在抽籤日那天作為自願者替她參賽的時候
我們都很感動
We were all very moved, I think, when
you volunteered for her at the Reaping.
她和你告別了嗎？
Did she come and say goodbye to you?
是的
Yes.
- 告別了
- 好的
- She did.
最後你跟她說什麼了？
And what did you say to her in the end?
我告訴她會盡全力贏得比賽
I told her that I would try to win.
為了她
That I would try to win for her.
當然
Of course you did.
你會盡力的
And try you will.
女士們，先生們，來自第12區的
Ladies and gentlemen, from District 12,
凱特尼斯·埃弗丁，燃燒女孩！
Katniss Everdeen, The Girl on Fire!
你做到了，親愛的，不可思議
You did it, darling. That was incredible.
謝謝
Thank you.
幹得漂亮，寶貝
Nice job, sweetheart.
謝謝
Thank you.
衣服不錯
Nice dress, too.
- 沒說你
- 請大家歡迎皮塔·莫拉克
- Not yours.
- Please welcome Peeta Mellark!
皮塔，歡迎
Peeta, welcome.
你怎麼找到凱匹特的？別跟我說「看地圖找的」
How are you finding The Capitol?
And don't say, "With a map. "
當然不是，這裏和家不一樣
It's different.
It's very different than back home.
不一樣，你指哪方面？舉個例子
Different. In what way? Give us an example.
好的，淋浴感覺挺古怪的
Okay. Well, the showers here are weird.
- 淋浴？
- 是的
- The showers?
- Yes.
咱們的淋浴不一樣
We have different showers.
有個問題想問你，凱撒
你聞我身上有玫瑰的味道嘛？
I have a question for you, Caesar.
Do I smell like roses to you?
- 再近一點
- 好
- Take a whiff?
- All right.
- 聞到了嗎？
- 嗯，我聞起來有玫瑰的味道嘛？
- You see?
- Yes. Do I smell like it?
- 你的聞起來一定比我強
- 那是，我在這呆的比你久
- You definitely smell better than I do.
- Well, I've lived here longer.
有道理
That makes sense.
真有趣，皮塔，和我說說
Very funny. So, Peeta, tell me,
在家有沒有對你來講意義特殊的女孩子？
is there a special girl back home?
沒，沒有，算不上
No. No. Not really.
沒有？我一點也不信，看看這張臉
No? I don't believe it for a second.
Look at that face.
像你這麼帥的小伙子，皮塔，招了吧
Handsome man like you. Peeta, tell me.
額，有…
Well, there...
我一直迷戀著一個女孩
There is this one girl
that I've had a crush on forever.
但實際上我並不認為她能認識我，直到抽籤日那天
But I don't think she actually recognized me
until the Reaping.
我來告訴你吧，皮塔
Well, I'll tell you what, Peeta.
從競技場走出去你就會贏得想要的東西
You go out there and you win this thing,
當你回家的時候，他一定會和你在一起的
and when you get home,
she'll have to go out with you.
對嗎？朋友們
Right, folks?
謝謝，但我並不覺得獲勝能幫什麼忙
Thanks, but I don't think winning's
gonna help me at all.
怎麼呢？
And why not?
因為她和我都在這
Because she came here with me.
真不走運
Well, that's bad luck.
的確是這樣
Yeah, it is.
- 祝你一切順利
- 謝謝
- And I wish you all the best of luck.
- Thank you.
皮塔·莫拉克
Peeta Mellark.
來自第12區！
District 12!
剛才是怎麼回事？
What the hell was that?
之前你不和我說話，現在你又說喜歡我？
You don't talk to me,
and then you say you have a crush on me?
你說你想獨立訓練，這是你想做的嗎？
You say you want to train alone?
Is that how you want to play?
住手！住手！
Stop it! Stop it!
- 咱倆把話說清楚！
- 嘿！
- Let's start right now!
- Hey!
- 他在幫你
- 他讓我看起來很脆弱
- He did you a favor.
- He made me look weak.
他使你看起來令人滿意
像你這種情況，不能傷心，寶貝
He made you look desirable,
which in your case, can't hurt, sweetheart.
他說的對，凱特尼斯
He's right, Katniss.
當然沒錯
Of course I'm right.
我可以出賣你們這對倒霉情侶
Now, I can sell the star-crossed lovers
from District 12...
我倆不是情侶
We are not star-crossed lovers.
這是電視節目！
It's a television show!
和他相愛也許會得到贊助商的青睞
And being in love with that boy
might just get you sponsors,
這樣才能讓你們保命
which could save your damn life.
好吧，你還在這幹什麼？
Okay. Why don't you get out of here?
也許明天我能拯救你們兩個
Maybe I can deliver you both
in one piece tomorrow.
禮貌點！
Manners!
你也沒睡？
You, too?
嘿
Hey.
睡不著嗎？
Can't sleep?
是啊，睡不著。
No. Of course not.
對於你的追求我很抱歉
I'm sorry I went after you.
你知道的，那只是在恭維你
You know, I meant that as a compliment.
我懂
I know.
聽他們的話吧
Listen to them.
嗯
Yeah.
我只是不想讓他們改變我
I just don't want them to change me.
他們怎麼改變你了？
How would they change you?
不知道，他們使我變得有點不像我了
I don't know.
They'd turn me into something I'm not.
我只是不想在遊戲里變成另外一個人，你懂嗎？
I just don't want to be
another piece in their game, you know?
你的意思是不殺任何人？
You mean you won't kill anyone?
不
No.
我是說我確定不會殺人的，和其他人一樣
I mean, I'm sure I would,
just like anybody else
當比賽開始時
when the time came,
我仍希望可以通過一種方式來向他們傳達
but I just keep wishing
that I could think of a way to show them
我並不屬於他們
that they don't own me.
即使我要死了，我也要做我自己
If I'm gonna die, I want to still be me.
你覺得有道理嗎？
Does that make any sense?
是啊
Yeah.
只是我還沒想過這些
I just can't afford to think like that.
我還有妹妹
I have my sister.
我知道
Yeah, I know.
咱們明天見吧
I guess I'll see you tomorrow.
明天見
See you tomorrow.
他們會把所有物品放在豐饒角前面的開口處
（註：豐饒角，位於比賽起點的建築，四周放有生存物資。）
They'll put all kinds of stuff right in front,
right in the mouth of the Cornucopia.
在那還有一把弓箭，你別去拿它
There'll even be a bow there. Don't go for it.
為什麼不能拿？
Why not?
遊戲剛開始會有一場大屠殺
你會被捲進去的
It's a bloodbath.
They're trying to pull you in.
這不是你一個人的遊戲
That's not your game.
你要轉身快跑，找個高地，尋找水源
You turn, run, find high ground,
look for water.
水是你最好的新朋友
Water's your new best friend.
別提前走基座上走下來，他們會把你吹上天的
Don't step off that pedestal early
or they'll blow you sky high.
我不會的
I won't.
凱特尼斯，你能做到的
Katniss, you can do this.
謝謝
Thanks.
伸出手臂
Give me your arm.
- 伸出手臂
- 這是什麼？
- Give me your arm.
- What is that?
追蹤器
Your tracker.
準備就緒
We're up.
We're up!
好的，還有不到一分鐘，夥計們
最後檢查一遍
All right. Less than a minute, people.
Final checks.
還有15秒，準備起飛
There are 15 out. They are flying.
這
Here.
謝謝
Thank you.
30秒
Thirty seconds.
我被禁止賭博
如果我可以下個賭注的話，一定賭你贏
I'm not allowed to bet,
but if I could, I'd bet on you.
20秒
Twenty seconds.
10秒
Ten seconds.
好的，他們進管道了
Okay, they're in the tubes.
50, 49, 48, 47,
46, 45, 44, 43,
42, 41, 40,
39, 38, 37, 36,
35, 34, 33, 32,
31, 30, 29, 28,
27, 26, 25,
24, 23, 22...
又是一次熟悉的噩耗
And, of course,
there's the familiar "boom" of the cannon,
屏幕上標記的是挑戰失敗的貢品
which marks the end
of another fallen Tribute.
...eight...
...nine...
...10...
...11...
...12.
25？收到
Twenty-five? Got it.
他在移動
He's moving now.
在第一個8小時內有13名選手挑戰失敗
Well, that makes 13 gone
in the first eight hours.
克勞迪亞斯，我想我看到一個正在逐步形成聯盟
And Claudius,
I think I see an alliance forming.
等下！你看到她的表情了嗎？
Wait! Did you see the look on her face?
- 你怎麼知道她在那？
- 看到火光了嗎？
- How stupid can you get?
- A fire?
「不！求求你，別殺我！不！」
"Oh, no! Please don't kill me! Oh, no!"
真令人印象深刻
That's actually a good impression.
嘿，小白臉！
Hey, lover boy!
- 你確定她走的是這條路嗎？
- 我確定
- You sure she went this way?
- Yeah, I'm sure.
最好沒錯
You better be.
那是她佈置的陷阱，我在那後面找到的
Yeah, that was her snare
we found back there.
我們現在怎麼不把他幹掉呢？
Are you sure we shouldn't just kill him now?
算了，有他在我們才能找到那女孩
Nah. He's our best chance of finding her.
走吧
Let's go.
先生？
Sir?
她一直在競技場的邊緣徘徊
She is almost at the edge.
離她最近的貢品也有2公里遠
Two kilometers away
from the nearest Tribute.
咱們得讓她掉頭
Let's turn her around.
另一個準備，開始計時，1，2
Cueing another. On my count. One, two...
她往左側去了
She's heading towards the left flank.
好的，能在那放棵樹嗎？
Okay. Can you give me a tree right there?
可以，準備放樹
Sure. Cueing tree.
她在那
She's almost there.
露西婭，準備加農炮
Lucia, get a cannon ready.
在那！她在那！
There she is! There she is!
- 她是我的！
- 先到先得！
- She's mine!
- Not if I get her first!
- 你往哪跑？
- 她是我的！
- Where you gonna go?
- Mine!
把池塘翻個遍，一定要找到她
Fish out of the pond!
And someone found her.
- 她在那！
- 耶！
- There she is!
- Yeah!
我們來啦！
Here we go!
- 往哪跑？
- 抓住他，卡托！
- Where you going, huh?
- Get her, Cato!
你以為能跑哪去？
Where do you think you're going?
往哪跑，寶貝
Where you going, baby?
3點鐘方向
Three o'clock.
- 你去哪，燃燒女孩？
- 我們抓到她了！
- Where you going, Girl on Fire?
- We got her!
埃弗丁小姐，我會抓住你的！
Miss Everdeen, I'm gonna get you!
爬那麼高無濟於事的，凱特尼斯
That's not gonna help you up there, Katniss.
你想往哪去啊？
Where are you going?
- 去抓她！
- 你能行的
- Go get her, man!
- You are so done.
卡托，上！
Just get her, Cato!
- 他來抓你了，凱特尼斯
- 看把她急的
- He's gonna get you, Katniss.
- Look at her scurry.
快逮到她了
Right up there.
- 殺了她！
- 繼續爬啊
- Kill her!
- Just go, keep going!
加油，卡托
- Go, Cato.
- Come on, Cato.
- 她就在那了
- 卡托！加油！卡托！
- She's right there.
- Go, Cato! Come on, Cato!
快到了
You got this.
爬啊！
Go! He's got this.
- 殺了她，卡托！抓住她，卡托！
- 上啊！
- Kill her, Cato! Just get her, Cato!
- Go! Go!
- 把她弄下來！
- 快爬啊！
- Take her down!
- Go! Go!
- 就快到了，卡托！
- 加油，殺了她！
- You got this, Cato!
- Come on, kill her!
我來取你小命了！
I'm coming for you!
加油，卡托！
Come on, Cato!
我自己來
I'll do it myself.
讓我來
Give me that before...
- 把她射下來
- 加油，射啊！
- Get her.
- Come on. Come on, come on!
你們應該把刀扔上來試試！
Maybe you should throw the sword!
我們等她下來吧
Let's just wait her out.
過段時間她會下來的，否則就得餓死
She's gotta come down at some point.
It's that or starve to death.
然後我們再找她算賬
We'll just kill her then.
好的
Okay.
誰去生把火
Somebody make a fire.
- 我們就在這露營
- 快去生把火
- Let's make camp over here!
- Hurry up with the fire.
小孩子
Boys.
[把這些都敷在傷口上，活下去 - 黑密斯]
[APPLY GENEROUSLY AND STAY ALIVE - H]
（註：降落傘補給是因為獲得觀眾
和贊助商的青睞才有機會獲得的）
謝謝
Thank you.
克勞迪亞斯，我想那些是殺人蜂，沒錯吧？
Claudius, I think those are tracker jackers
Am I wrong?
- 它們相當有殺傷力
- 很致命
- Those things are very lethal.
- Very.
對於不瞭解的朋友，我再介紹一下
For those of you who don't know,
殺人蜂是經過基因改良過的黃蜂
毒液可以引起灼熱似的疼痛
tracker jackers are genetically engineered
wasps whose venom causes searing pain,
強勁的幻覺，在極端情況下甚至可以導致死亡
powerful hallucinations,
and in extreme cases, death.
跑！
Run!
快跑啊！
凱特尼斯，快跑！
Katniss, go!
離開這，快走！
你在想什麼，快走！
Get out of here! Go!
What are you doing? Go!
不但極具殺傷力，而且只需一隻殺人蜂的毒液
Not only is it lethal,
but the venom of a tracker jacker sting
也能令人產生強勁的幻覺
can produce powerful hallucinations.
媽媽，別只是坐在那看我！
說點什麼吧！
Mom, don't just sit there and look at me!
Please say something!
凱特尼斯，快跑！
Katniss, go!
離開這，快走！
你在想什麼，快走！
Get out of here! Go!
What are you doing? Go!
茹？
Rue?
沒事，我不會傷害你的
It's okay. I'm not gonna hurt you.
我的也給你吧？
You want mine, too?
不用了
No, that's okay.
給
Here.
謝謝
Thanks.
我昏迷多久了？
How long was I asleep?
好幾天了，我幫你換了兩次樹葉
Couple of days. I changed your leaves twice.
謝謝
Thank you.
我昏迷這幾天都發生什麼了？
So what happened while I was out?
第1區的女孩和第10區的男孩
The girl from 1 and the boy from 10.
和我一起來的男孩呢？
And the boy from my district?
他沒事，我想他沿著河邊往下遊走了
Yeah, he's okay.
I think he's down by the river.
那些都是真的嗎？
Is all of that true?
什麼？
What?
你們倆？
You and him?
卡托和其他人在哪？
So where are Cato and the others?
他們把所有補給品放在河邊
They got all their supplies
down by the lake.
堆成很大的錐型
It's piled up in this great big pyramid.
聽起來很誘人
That sounds tempting.
這些樹枝可以很快的燃燒起來
Now, this green stuff
is gonna smoke like crazy,
一旦你點燃它了，就接著去點燃下一堆
so as soon as you light it,
move on to the next fire.
點燃最後這堆後，我會在那跟你會合
Light this one last,
and I'll meet you back over there.
好的
Right.
然後當他們去抓我們的時候，我會摧毀他們的補給品
And then I'll destroy their stuff
while they're chasing us.
一旦我們當中的一個被抓了，需要一個暗號
We need a signal
in case one of us gets held up.
好，什麼暗號？
Okay. Like what?
看著
Here. Watch this.
學舌鳥，太棒了
Mockingjays. That's great.
在家的時候，我們一直用它們做暗號
Back home,
we use them to signal all the time.
你來試試
You try.
很好，一旦我們聽見這聲音
Okay, so if we hear that,
就表示我倆都沒事，很快便會再見面的
it means we're okay
and we'll be back real soon.
我們會沒事的
We're gonna be okay.
晚餐見
Hey, I'll see you for supper.
- 好的
-Okay-
夥計們，看吶！這呢
過來，看這邊！
Guys. Guys, look! Over here.
Come on, come on. Look!
我們走
Let's go.
你要保持警惕在我們回來之前別離開
You stay guard and don't move
until we can get back.
我倒想看看她能否搞定這個陷阱
I want to see if she's gonna figure out
this booby trap.
是啊，看起來這一大堆好吃的旁邊
Yes. It seems they've reburied their mines
埋了不少地雷
around that big pile of goodies.
她一定能搞定的，不是麼？
She's certainly figured it out, hasn't she?
我不知道發生了什麼
I don't know what happened.
- 究竟是怎麼回事？
- 我不知道
- What the hell happened?
- I don't know!
補給品全毀了！
Our stuff!
凱特尼斯！
Katniss!
凱特尼斯，救命！
Katniss, help!
凱特尼斯！
Katniss!
凱特尼斯！救救我！
Katniss! Help!
凱特尼斯！
Katniss!
沒事了
It's okay. It's okay.
沒事的，你很好，明白嗎？
You're okay. You're okay. You're fine. See?
會好起來的
It's okay. You're okay.
一切都會好的
You're okay. You're okay.
你把他們的食物毀掉了嗎？
Did you blow up the food?
片甲不留
Every bit of it.
太好了
Good.
你贏定了
You have to win.
你能唱歌給我聽嗎？
Can you sing?
好的
Okay.
在草叢深處
Deep in the meadow
在柳樹下
Under the willows
草墊床
A bed of grass
軟軟的綠枕頭
A soft green pillow
把頭放上去
Lay down your head
閉上你的眼
and close your eyes
當你睜開眼，陽光……
And when they open, the sun...
對不起
I'm sorry.
[11區]
[DISTRICT 11]
別殺她，這樣只能多一個犧牲者而已
Don't kill her. You'll just create a martyr.
看起來我們已經有一個了
Well, it seems we've already got one.
關於11區的傳言我也聽說了
如果按我說的做可以避免把你捲入是非
I hear these rumors out of District 11.
This could get away from you.
你想怎麼樣？
What do you want?
那有很多憤怒的群眾
You have a lot of anger out there.
我想你應該知道如何處理這幫暴徒
之前你也經歷過
I know you know how to handle a mob.
You've done it before.
如果你不能嚇跑他們，就支持他們吧
If you can't scare them,
give them something to root for.
比如？
Such as?
浪漫的愛情
Young love.
你怎麼像個窮鬼一樣？
So you like an underdog?
大家都喜歡窮鬼
Everyone likes an underdog.
我不喜歡
I don't.
你去過那嗎？10區？11區？12區？
Have you been out there? 10? 11? 12?
沒去過
Not personally. No.
我去過
Well, I have.
那有很多窮人
There are lots of underdogs.
煤也不少
Lots of coal, too.
農作物，礦產，都是我們需要的東西
Grow crops, minerals, things we need.
窮人很多
There are lots of underdogs.
我想如果你看到他們
And I think if you could see them,
就不會支持他們了
you would not root for them either.
我欣賞你
I like you.
當心點
Be careful.
貢品請注意，貢品請注意
Attention, Tributes. Attention.
只有1名獲勝者的比賽規則暫定廢除
The regulations requiring a single victor
have been suspended.
從現在起，允許有兩名勝者
From now on, two victors may be crowned,
只要兩人來自於同一區
if both originate from the same district.
僅此通告
This will be the only announcement.
皮塔
Peeta.
天吶！皮塔！皮塔！
Oh, my God! Peeta! Peeta!
嗨
Hi.
沒事了
It's okay.
怎麼弄的？
What was it?
刀傷
A sword.
糟透了，不是麼？
It's bad, huh?
會好起來的
It's gonna be fine.
凱特尼斯
Katniss.
- 凱特尼斯
- 不！
- Katniss.
- No!
我不會離開你
再也不會那麼做了
I'm not gonna leave you.
I'm not gonna do that.
為什麼？
Why not?
在這沒人會找到你
Nobody's gonna find you in here.
他們已經發現我一次了
They already found me.
我們會給你弄些藥
We'll just get you some medicine.
凱特尼斯，我沒弄到多少降落傘補給
Katniss, I don't get many parachutes.
我們會有辦法的
We'll figure something out.
比如說？
Like what?
會有的
Something.
[這也算接吻嗎？ -黑密斯]
[YOU CALL THAT A KISS? - H]
- 是藥嗎？
- 不，是湯
- Medicine?
- No. Soup.
我來餵你吧
I'll do it.
味道真好
That's nice.
曾經你有恩於我
You fed me once.
我一直在想
I think about that all the time.
我怎麼能把麵包丟給你呢
How I tossed you that bread.
- 皮塔
- 我應該把它送給你
- Peeta...
- I should have gone to you.
我應該冒雨走到你面前然後……
I should have just gone out in the rain and...
你好像有點發燒
You feel hot.
我還記得第一次見到你是什麼樣子
I remember the first time I saw you.
你梳兩條辮子
Your hair was in two braids instead of one.
我還記得當你在音樂課唱歌的時候
And I remember when you sang
in the music assembly.
老師說「誰知道山谷之歌？」
"Who knows The Valley Song?」
The teacher said,
你第一個把手舉起來
And your hand shot straight up.
別說了
Stop.
從那之後，我每天都會看著你回家
After that,
I watched you going home every day.
每天都是
Every day-
說點什麼吧
Well, say something.
我不擅長和別人交流
I'm not good at saying something.
那就到這來
Then come here.
來吧
Please.
即使我沒有…
Even if I don't make it...
別說了
Stop it.
貢品請注意，貢品請注意
Attention, Tributes. Attention.
明天日出時分，在豐饒角
Commencing at sunrise,
there will be a feast tomorrow
會有一場盛筵
at the Cornucopia.
想參加的話並不輕鬆
This will be no ordinary occasion.
你們每個人都要拿出真本事
Each of you needs something desperately.
我們是很慷慨的
And we plan to be generous hosts.
會有你需要的藥品
Your medicine.
你別自己去
You're not going alone.
你需要它，你現在無法行走
Yeah? You need it, and you can't walk.
凱特尼斯，別為了我拿自己的性命冒險，我不會讓你去的
Katniss, you're not gonna risk
your life for me. I'm not gonna let you.
如果換做是你，也會這麼做，不是嗎？
You would do it for me. Wouldn't you?
為什麼要這麼做？
Why are you doing this?
（註：之前的降落傘裏導師的
紙條上寫著「這也算是接吻嗎？」）
（這句話的意思是提醒凱特尼斯即便做秀也要做足，
要想活命，必須和皮塔在一起，）
（於是凱特尼斯回到山洞又給了皮塔深深的一吻。）
現在我更不可能讓你去了
Now there's no way I'm letting you go.
皮塔…
Peeta...
求你了
Please.
留下吧
Stay.
好吧
Okay.
我不走
I'll stay.
哦，天吶！
Oh, God!
你的男朋友呢？
Where's lover boy?
我知道了，你是為他而來的，對不對？
I see. You were gonna help him, right?
太感人了。你知道嗎，救不了你那位小朋友
是多麼糟糕的一件事
Well, that's sweet. You know, it's too bad
that you couldn't help your little friend.
她叫什麼來著？
That little girl? What was her name again?
茹？
Rue?
就是她，是我們殺了她
Yeah, well, we killed her.
現在我來幹掉你
And now we're gonna kill you.
你殺了她？
You kill her?
- 不！
- 我聽見你說的了！
- No!
- I heard you!
- 卡托！卡托！
- 你說了她的名字！
- Cato! Cato!
- You said her name!
是你說的！
You said her name!
就這一次
Just this time, 12.
為了茹
For Rue.
皮塔，我找到藥了
Peeta, I got it. I got the medicine.
- 你怎麼了
- 沒怎麼
- What happened to you?
- I'm fine.
不，你受傷了，發生什麼了？
No, you're not. What happened?
2區的女孩，對我丟了一把飛刀，沒事的
The girl from 2, she threw a knife. I'm okay.
你就不應該去
你說過你不會去的
You shouldn't have gone.
You said you weren't gonna go.
你的傷好像更糟了
You got worse.
對不起
I'm sorry.
你也需要抹一點
You need some of that, too.
我沒事
I'm okay.
感覺好多了
That feels better.
好的，該你了
Okay. Now you.
- 我不用
- 來吧，你也抹點吧
- I'm okay.
- No, come on, you need it, too.
來
Come on.
好吧
All right.
嗨
Hi.
你痊癒得這麼快
You're so much better.
哦，天吶！皮塔
Oh, my God, Peeta.
我感覺好像沒受過傷一樣
I hardly feel anything.
我們能回家了
We could go home.
是的，我們是這組裏僅存的兩個人
We could. We're the only team left.
我們要回家了
We could go home.
我們現在得知斯瑞斯離開了
（註：斯瑞斯，11區男性參賽者，
他能活著的唯一依靠就是一身蠻力）
We know Thresh took off.
卡托會去豐饒角那
Cato's gonna be by the Cornucopia.
他不會到自己沒去過的地方
He's not gonna go someplace
he doesn't know.
福克斯費斯不一定在哪呢
（註：福克斯費斯，5區女性參賽者，
靠頭腦作戰，擅長軍事佈局與策略）
Foxface, she could be anywhere.
咱們應該在這附近打獵
帶的食物都吃光了
We should probably hunt around here.
We don't have any food left.
好吧，我來射箭吧
Okay, I'll take the bow.
開玩笑罷了，我去採點果子
I'm just kidding. I'll go pick some stuff.
皮塔？
Peeta?
皮塔！
Peeta!
你沒事吧？
Are you okay?
- 我聽到加農炮的聲音了，我以為…
- 不
- I heard the cannon. I thought...
- No.
那是毒漿果，皮塔！吃它會要了你的命！
That's Nightlock, Peeta!
You'd be dead in a minute!
我不知道
I didn't know.
該死的，你差點嚇死我了
You scared me to death. Damn you.
對不起
I'm sorry.
我還不知道她在一直跟蹤我
I never even knew she was following me.
她真聰明
She's clever.
聰明極了
Too clever.
- 你在幹什麼？
- 也許卡托會喜歡這些漿果
- What are you doing?
- Maybe Cato likes berries, too.
現在幾點了？
What time is it?
剛到下午
A little after noon.
為什麼天色這麼黑？
Why is it getting so dark?
看來要盡早結束這場爭鬥了
Must be in a hurry to end it.
- 準備好了嗎， 露西婭？
- 在這，先生
- You ready, Lucia?
- Right here, sir.
很好，太棒了
Well, that's great.
- 可以把它放到競技場嗎？
- 沒問題
- Now can you put that in the middle?
- Sure.
就是這樣，效果一定不錯
That's it. That's excellent.
你聽見了嗎？
Did you hear that?
那是什麼聲音？
What was that?
慘叫
It's the finale.
我們走吧
Let's go.
快跑
Go.
凱特尼斯！
Katniss!
上去！
Here!
來啊，射我啊
Go on. Shoot.
我們倆都掉下去，你就贏了
Then we both go down and you'd win.
來吧，反正我死定了
Go on. I'm dead anyway.
一向如此，對嗎？
I always was, right?
直到現在我才知道
I didn't know that till now.
怎麼會這樣呢？這就是他們想要的嗎？
How is that? Is that what they want?
- 不
- 不，不要
- No.
- No, no.
我也可以把他的脖子扭斷的
I could still do this.
我會的
再殺一個又能怎樣
One more kill.
這使我唯一知道怎麼做的事
It's the only thing I know how to do.
為我所在地的區域帶來榮耀
Bring pride to my district.
這並不重要
Not that it matters.
求你了！
Please!
不！
No!
求你殺了我吧！
Please!
貢品請注意，貢品請注意
Attention. Attention, Tributes.
規則稍有變化
There has been a slight rule change.
之前允許同一區域的兩人
The previous revision,
可作為勝者的規則
allowing for two victors
from the same district,
已被廢除
has been revoked.
新規則規定只允許有一名勝者，祝你們好運
Only one victor may be crowned. Good luck.
希望好運永遠站在你這邊
And may the odds be ever in your favor.
來吧
Go ahead.
只有一個人能回家
One of us should go home.
必須要有人作出犧牲，他們只要一個勝者
One of us has to die.
They have to have their victor.
不
No.
他們不能這樣
They don't.
為什麼總任由他們擺佈？
Why should they?
- 不！
- 相信我
- No!
- Trust me.
相信我
Trust me.
一起來？
Together?
一起
Together.
好的
Okay.
One...
Two...
Three.
住手！
Stop!
女士們，先生們，我來介紹一下
Ladies and gentlemen,
may I present the winners
第74屆年度飢餓遊戲的勝者
of the 74th Annual Hunger Games.
他們對你並不滿意
They're not happy with you.
為什麼？因為我沒死嗎？
Why? Because I didn't die?
因為你讓他們出醜了
Because you showed them up.
好吧，對不起，我沒按規則辦事
Well, I'm sorry
it didn't go the way they planned.
- 我對他們也不滿意
- 凱特尼斯！
- I'm not very happy with them either.
- Katniss!
嚴肅一點，這不只是為了你自己
This is serious. Notjust for you.
他們不會就這麼輕易罷手的
They don't take these things lightly.
當他們問你的時候，你就說控制不住自己
When they ask,
you say you couldn't help yourself.
你和這個男孩很恩愛
You were so in love with this boy
不敢想像沒有他會是什麼樣子
that the thought of not being with him
was unthinkable.
如果失去他不如讓我去死，明白嗎？
You'd rather die than not be with him.
You understand?
當你在河邊找到他的時候是什麼感覺？
How did you feel
when you found him by that river?
感覺我是全世界最幸福的人
I felt like the happiest person in the world.
不敢想像沒有他生活會變成什麼樣子
I couldn't imagine life without him.
你呢，皮塔？
And what about you, Peeta?
他救了我一命
She saved my life.
我們拯救了彼此
We saved each other.
女士們，先生們，第74屆年度飢餓遊戲總冠軍是
Ladies and gentlemen,
the star-crossed lovers from District 12,
來自第12區的倒霉情侶！
this year's victors
of the 74th Annual Hunger Games!
恭喜你們
Congratulations.
謝謝
Thank you.
胸針很漂亮
What a lovely pin.
謝謝，這是我們區域的饋贈
Thank you. It's from my district.
他們一定會為你感到非常驕傲的
They must be very proud of you.
回去了我們會怎麼樣？
So what happens when we get back?
不知道，我想我們應該試著忘記這段經歷
I don't know. I guess we try to forget.
我不想忘掉
I don't want to forget.
=-全片完，謝謝觀賞-=
更多精彩影視，盡在HDCHINA.ORG